Alfred Balk Papers
Alfred Balk Papers
1925-2010
Balk, Alfred, 1930-2010.
19 linear ft.
Research material, writings, audiorecordings, periodicals, amassed by journalist, editor and radio scholar Alfred Balk over the course of his writing and teaching career.
3192476
Biographical History
Alfred Balk (1930-2010) was an American journalist, editor, and non-fiction author in several fields including radio and television history.
Born in Oskaloosa, Iowa on July 24, 1930, Alfred Balk graduated from Northwestern University with a BA and MA in journalism. He was feature editor and editor at large for the Saturday Review (1966-1969), editor of the Columbia Journalism Review (1969-1973) and founding editor of the World Press Review, where he worked from 1973 to 1986. Later in his career he served as managing editor of IEEE Spectrum, the magazine of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (1989-1991). In 1963 Balk and Alex Haley co-wrote "Black Merchants of Hate," an article on Malcolm X and the Nation of Islam; according to the New York Times, the article "was a major factor in Haley's future book, The Autobiography of Malcolm X.
In addition to his journalistic pursuits, he wrote for national magazines including the Saturday Evening Post and Harper's, was the author of several books, and taught at both Syracuse University and Columbia University.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alfred Balk Papers consists of research files, most related to Balk's book The Rise of Radio; printed material (books, catalogs, newsletters, periodicals); recordings in various media (VHS tapes, audiocassettes, record albums) of classic radio and television programs and special broadcasts relating to the topic; oral history project interviews; and radio advertising premiums from Ovaltine, Wheaties, and other products.
The collection has received minimal processing, and the inventory which follows is a simple box listing.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has been arranged according to the groupings given above, but within the groupings little other arrangement has been done. Folders for the most part retain the donor's original titles and ordering.
Related Material
has extensive holdings in journalism and in radio and television history. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
A number of published books and monographs have been transferred to Rare Books or to the general circulating collection for cataloging. For a complete listing, please refer to the finding aids files, or search for the phrase "Gift of Alfred Balk."
Subject and Genre Headings
Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Balk, Alfred, 1930-2010.; Rise of radio.; Popular culture -- United States.; Radio -- History.; Radio broadcasting -- United States -- History.; Radio programs -- United States -- History.; 78 rpm records.; Audiocassettes.; Catalogs (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Long-playing records.; Manuscripts for publication.; Newsletters.; Oral histories (literary works); Research notes.; Sound recordings.; VHS.; Videocassettes.; Journalist.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alfred Balk, 2010.
Inventory
- Research files
  - General
    - "About the Collection" by Alfred Balk, (typewritten manuscript) (Box 1)
    - Interviews
      - Transcripts and interview notes (Box 1)
      - Source tapes, (audiocassettes) (Box 16-17)
    - Picture files (Box 1)
  - For book, The Rise of Radio
    - General (Box 2)
    - End notes (Box 2)
    - Introduction (Box 2)
    - Chapters 1-23 (Box 3)
    - Chapters 24-34 (Box 4)
    - Archives/people to contact (Box 4)
    - Radio's roots (Box 4)
    - Pre-radio (Box 4)
    - Embryo years (Box 5)
    - Stations (Box 6)
    - Networks (Box 7)
    - Controversies (Box 7)
    - Programs/stars (Box 8)
    - Programs/stars (continued) (Box 9)
    - Personalities (Box 10)
    - Before the fall (Box 10)
    - Networks/transition to TV (Box 10)
    - Statistics (Box 10)
    - Issues (Box 10)
    - Issues (continued) (Box 11)
    - Network anniversary commemorative publications (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Barlow, William Voiceover: the making of Black radio, Temple University Press, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Barnouw, Erik, Media marathon, Duke University Press, 1996 (Box 13)
    - Barnouw, Erik, The image empire: A history of broadcasting in the United States volume 3, Oxford University Press, 1970 (Box 13)
    - Brokenshire, Norman, This is Norman Brokenshire: an unvarnished self-portrait, D. McKay Co., 1954 (Box 13)
    - Cohen, Hal L. ed. 1922 Montgomery Ward catalogue. Reprinted in its original form..., HC Publishers, 1969 (Box 13)
    - Cox, Jim, Frank and Anne Hummert's radio factory: the programs and personalities of broadcasting's most prolific producers, McFarland & Co., 2003 (Box 13)
    - Douglas, Alan, Radio manufacturers of the 1920s (3 vol.), Vestal Press 1991 (Box 13)
    - Douglas, Susan J., Inventing American broadcasting, 1899-1922, Johns Hopkins University Press, 1987 (Box 13)
    - Greb, Gordon B., Charles Herrold, inventor of radio broadcasting, McFarland & Co., 2003 (Box 13)
    - Hilliard, Robert L., The quieted voice: the rise and demise of localism in American radio, Southern Illinois University Press, 2005 (Box 13)
    - Hilmes, Michele, Radio voices: American broadcasting, University of Minnesota Press, 1997 (Box 13)
    - Shayon, Robert Lewis, Odyssey in prime time: a life in twentieth century media, Waymark Press, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Slide, Anthony, Great radio personalities in historic photographs, Vestal Press, 1988 (Box 13)
    - Sterling, Christopher, Stay tuned: a concise history of American broadcasting, Wadsworth, 1990, inscribed by author (Box 13)
    - Terrace, Vincent, Radio program openings and closings, 1931-1972, McFarland & Co., 2003 (Box 13)
    - Tumbusch, Tom, Tomart's price guide to radio premium and cereal box collectibles, including comic character, pulp hero, and other premiums, Tomart Publications, 1991 (Box 13)
    - United States. Bureau of Human Nutrition, Aunt Sammy's radio recipes revised, U.S. Government Printing Office, 1931 (Box 13)
    - Weaver, Pat, The best seat in the house: the golden years in radio and television, Knopf, 1994 (Box 13)
    - Wertheim, Arthur Frank, Radio comedy, Oxford University Press, 1979 (Box 13)
  - Catalogs
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Newsletters and other publications of broadcasting-related organizations and fan clubs
    - Antique Radio Club of Illinois (Box 14)
    - Antique Wireless Association (Box 14)
    - California Historical Radio Society (Box 14)
    - The Cinnamon Bear Brigade (Box 14)
    - Friends of Vic and Sade (Box 14)
    - Golden Radio Buffs of Maryland, Inc (Box 14)
    - International Jack Benny Fan Club (Box 14)
    - Library of American Broadcasting (Box 14)
    - Media Heritage Archives (Box 14)
    - Mid-Atlantic Antique Radio Club (Box 14)
    - Museum of Broadcasting (Box 14)
    - National Lum & Abner Society (Box 14)
    - Old Time Radio Club (Box 14)
    - Pittsburgh Antique Radio Society (Box 14)
    - Radio and Television Museum Bowie, MD (Box 14)
    - Radio Enthusiasts of Puget Sound (Box 14)
    - Radio Historical Society of Colorado (Box 14)
    - Society to Preserve and Encourage Radio Drama, Variety and Comedy (Box 14)
  - Periodicals
    - Billboard, Jan 20, 1934 (Box 15)
    - Broadcasting, Dec 9,1991 (Box 15)
    - Colliers, Jul 5, 1947 (Box 15)
    - Hit Parader, Apr 1943 (Box 15)
    - Model Fun, Jul 1955 (Box 15)
    - Literary Digest, 9/19/1925; 10/31/1925,; 1/30/1926,; 5/22/1926,; 5/29/1926 (Box 15)
    - Look, 2/1/1949; 1/2/1951 (Box 15)
    - Nostalgia Digest, Spring 2010 (Box 15)
    - Popular Radio, Sept 1922 (Box 15)
    - Radio Guide, 11/30/1935; 11/20/1937 (Box 15)
    - Radio Digest, 8/1/1930; June 1932; cover only for 1932 issue (Box 15)
    - Radio Mirror, 12/1/1946 (Box 15)
    - Radio News, Dec 1930 (Box 15)
    - Radio Romances, Jun 1945 (Box 15)
    - Radio Stars, Oct 1932 (Box 15)
    - Radio and Television Mirror, 8/1/1948; 7/1/1949 (Box 15)
    - Radio Television Mirror, Mar 1951 (Box 15)
    - Radio Topics, Sept 1922 (Box 15)
    - Radio-TV Mirror, Jan 1953 (Box 15)
    - Radioland, May 1934 (Box 15)
    - Sheet Music, Sept/Oct 1991; May/Jun 1995,; Sept/Oct 1995,; May/Jun 1996,; Nov/Dec 1996,; Sept/Oct 1997,; Nov/Dec 1998 (Box 15)
    - Tower Radio, Apr 1934 (Box 15)
    - Tune In, Oct 1945 (Box 15)
    - WLS Weekly, Mar 16, 1935 (Box 15)
- Media
  - Video cassettes
    - Amos and Andy: Check and Double Check, 1 VHS cassette (Box 16)
  - CDs and DVDs
    - Bill and Seemah Idelson: REPS Showcase (June 2005), 1 compact disc (Box 16)
    - Bill Idelson's Memorial (Writers Guild Theatre, 2/21/2008), 1 compact disc (Box 16)
    - Cincinnati Radio: The Nation's Station (1921-1941), 3 compact discs (Box 16)
    - Cincinnati Radio: The War Years (1941-1945), 2 compact discs (Box 16)
    - From the Nation's Capital (George Washington University), 1 compact disc (Box 16)
    - Franklyn MacCormack, Vols. 1-3, 5 compact discs (Box 16)
    - The Poet Laureate of Radio: An Interview with Norman Corwin, 1 DVD (Box 16)
    - Radio Classics: The Bickersons, 1 compact disc (Box 16)
    - Radio Classics: Lum & Abner, 1 compact disc (Box 16)
  - Phonograph records
    - The Jack Benny Album (Oversize 2)
    - Do It on the Radio (Oversize 2)
    - Edward R. Murrow: A Reporter Remembers (Vol. 1: The War Years) (Oversize 2)
    - Great Moments in Radio (Oversize 2)
    - I Can Hear It Now/The Sixties (Oversize 2)
    - Fibber McGee and Molly (Oversize 2)
    - The Nostalgic Sounds and Voices of Old Time Radio (Oversize 2)
    - Radio Plays the Plaza (Oversize 2)
    - Remember the Golden Days of Radio (2 vol.) (Oversize 2)
    - Vic and Sade (Oversize 2)
    - When Radio Was King: Mr. District Attorney (Oversize 2)
  - Audiocassettes, commercially produced
    - America Before TV: A Day from the Golden Age of Radio (September 21, 1939), 12 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Baby Snooks, 6 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - The Best of Abbott and Costello, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - The Best of Fred Allen, 2 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Comedy Classics: Abbot and Costello, Vol. 1, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - Duffy's Tavern, 6 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Golden Age of Comedy, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - Greatest Old-Time Radio Christmas Shows, Selected by Andy Williams: The Jack Benny Program (12/5/1954), 1 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Greatest Shows of the 20th Century, Selected by Walter Cronkite: The Life of Riley (6/19/1948), 2 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - The Best of Groucho Marx, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - I Can Hear It Now, Featuring Edward R. Murrow: 30 Years of Audible History (1919-1949), 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - The Jack Benny Program, 2 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Mercury Theatre On the Air: War of the Worlds and Dracula, 2 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - National Barn Dance, 2 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Old Radio Classics: Radio Commercials, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
    - Old Time Radio's Greatest Shows, 20 audio cassettes (Box 16)
    - Radio Reruns: CBS News Roundup: Pearl Harbor Attacked (12/7/1941) (Box 16)
    - The Red Skelton Show, 1 audio cassette (Box 16)
  - Audiocassettes, homemade
    - Programs
      - Abbott and Costello (Box 17)
      - The Fred Allen Show (Box 17)
      - Amos and Andy (Box 17)
      - The Andrew Sisters (Box 17)
      - Gene Autry (Box 17)
      - Avalon (Box 17)
      - Barn Dance (Box 17)
      - Baby Snooks (Box 17)
      - Jack Benny (Box 17)
      - Edgar Bergen (Box 17)
      - Milton Berle (Box 17)
      - Best of the Big Band Singers (Box 17)
      - Beulah (Box 17)
      - The Bickersons (Box 17)
      - Big Band Jam Sessions/Themes Like Old Times (Box 16)
      - Billion Dollar Show (Box 16)
      - Bob and Ray (Box 17)
      - Burns and Allen (Box 17)
      - Can You Top This? (Box 17)
      - Judy Canova (Box 17)
      - Eddie Cantor (Box 17)
      - Jack Carson (Box 17)
      - Chamber Music Society of Lower Basin Street (Box 17)
      - Chase and Sanborn Hour (Box 17)
      - Dr. I.Q. (Box 17)
      - Dragnet (Box 17)
      - Duffy's Tavern (Box 17)
      - Jimmy Durante Show (Box 17)
      - Easy Aces (Box 17)
      - Good News of 1938 (Box 17)
      - Benny Goodman (Box 17)
      - Grand Ole Opry (Box 18)
      - Hawaii Calls (Box 18)
      - Bob Hope Show (Box 18)
      - I Love a Mystery (Box 18)
      - Information Please (Box 18)
      - George Jessel (Box 18)
      - Spike Jones Spotlight (Box 18)
      - Danny Kaye Show (Box 18)
      - Lone Ranger (Box 18)
      - Lum & Abner (Box 18)
      - Lux Radio Theatre (Box 18)
      - Majestic Theatre of the Air (Box 18)
      - Manhattan Merry Go Round (Box 18)
      - March of Time (Box 18)
      - Martin and Lewis (Box 18)
      - Maxwell House Showboat (Box 18)
      - Glenn Miller (Box 18)
      - Moon River (Box 18)
      - Henry Morgan Show (Box 18)
      - One Night Stand (Box 17)
      - Our Miss Brooks (Box 17)
      - Jack Paar Show (Box 17)
      - Philco Radio Hall of Fame (Box 17)
      - Red Ryder (Box 17)
      - Red Skelton Show (Box 17)
      - Kate Smith Show (Box 17)
      - Texaco Star Theatre (Box 17)
      - Town Hall Tonight (Box 17)
      - Rudy Vallee Hour (Box 17)
      - Victory Parade (Box 17)
      - The Village Store (Box 17)
      - Fred Waring (Box 17)
      - Paul Whiteman Presents (Box 17)
      - Ed Wynn (Box 17)
      - Your Hit Parade (Box 17)
    - Specials and commemorative, historical and anniversary broadcasts
      - And Now a word from Our Sponsor (Box 17)
      - Biography in Sound (Box 17)
      - Frank Bresee KNUS (Box 17)
      - Johnny Carson's Half Century of Comedy (Box 17)
      - CBS at 50 (Box 17)
      - Command Performance (Box 17)
      - Crowd Went Wild (Box 17)
      - Destination Freedom (Box 17)
      - GI Journal (Box 17)
      - Golden Days of Radio (Box 17)
      - Greek War Relief (Box 17)
      - Guest Star (Box 17)
      - Bob Hope Show Spoofs (Box 17)
      - I Can Hear It Now (Box 17)
      - Japanese Surrender, ABC (Box 17)
      - H. V. Kaltenborn, News (Box 17)
      - Jerome Kern Memorial (Box 17)
      - KDKA (Box 17)
      - KSAC Anniversary (Box 17)
      - Mutual, Don Lee Dedication (Box 17)
      - NBC 40th Anniversary (Box 17)
      - On a Note of Triumph (Box 17)
      - Radio Themes (Box 17)
      - Radio's First 50 Years (Box 17)
      - Radio's Superheroes at War (Box 17)
      - This Was Radio (Box 17)
      - USO Farewell Program (Box 17)
      - Voices of Two Game [ESPN] (Box 17)
      - World War II Chronicles (Box 17)
  - Oral History Project
    - Taped Interviews (Box 16-17)
- Radio advertising premiums
  - Hafner 1010-13 wind-up train set (green/copper) premium from Coco Wheats premium, Happy Hank program, circa 1945 (Oversize 1)
  - Enna Jettick Melodies songbook, Enna Jettick Shoes premium, 1930 (Oversize 1)
  - Little Orphan Annie's Song, Ovaltine premium, 1931 (Oversize 1)
  - Jack Armstrong Bombsight, Wheaties premium, 1942 (Oversize 1)
  - Jack Armstrong Hike/O/Meter, Wheaties premium, 1938 (Oversize 1)
  - Tom Mix Ralston Straight Shooter Compass, Ralston premium, 1936 (Oversize 1)